Center for Humanistic Education; Records ua443
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Center for Humanistic Education Records
1969-1973
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua443
6 cubic ft.
This collection consists of records documenting the finances of and the workshops and activities put on by the University at Albany's Center for Humanistic Education during its period of activity.
Biographical History
The University at Albany established the Center for Humanistic Education in 1969. Borne out of educational reform proposals in the 1960s, the Center was formed with the idea of helping to create an education system that was more "human-centered" and focused on teaching students in a way that would truly resonate with them. From its founding under the direction of Dr. Alfred Alschuler, the Center was loosely affiliated with the university and received much of its financing from state grants and registration payments for its workshops and presentations. The Center worked primarily with two-year colleges and high schools around New York State. One of the Humanistic Education Center's primary functions was to organize workshops at the University-owned Jesuit Retreat House in Glenmont, New York. Before its move to the Jesuit Retreat House in 1970, the Center had been based out of Richardson Hall on SUNY Albany's downtown campus. As the Center was only loosely affiliated with the University, it was dependent on grants from New York State for its funding. Drastic funding cuts in 1973 forced the Center to give up its lease on the Jesuit Retreat House and returned to the University campus. From there further staff cuts led to the dissolution of the program in either late 1973 or 1974.
Scope and Contents
The collections consists of the Center for Humanistic Education's records including: material on the Vocational Education program; workshop and program proposals as well as documentation of completed workshops and programs; meeting minutes, correspondence and memoranda; reports and presentations by staff members as well as budgetary documents and payment information regarding workshops. This collection also contains 3 16mm documentary films covering topics in education.
Arrangement of the Collection
Files in this collection have been maintained in their original order upon processing.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
humanism; UAlbany Centers & Institutes; Institute for Humanistic Studies
- Proposed Programs [1 of 2], 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Proposed Programs [2 of 2], Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Brochure, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Program Obligations Memo, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- SUNY-State Education Department, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Lifelong Opportunities for Career Education, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Labeled: Introduction, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Proposal Abstract of A Vocational Education Project, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- XICOM, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Program Synopsis 1st and 2nd Drafts, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Project Completion Report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Evaluation Questionnaires, 1973 April 14-1973 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Charts Re: Open Education, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bringing Career Education into Elementary Schools, Final Report, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Open Education Proposals and Proposal Summary, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Opinion Survey & Data Summary, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Projected Budget Estimates, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Open Classroom Workshops, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letters to G. Maybury Boces, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letters to Teachers, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letters to Parents, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- All Correspondence Re Open Education, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "After the Turn on What?" AND After the Turn On What?, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Humanistic Inservice Project, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Inservice Project (1 of 2), 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Inservice Project (2 of 2), 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Humanistic Education, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Legal Info-Letters Etc., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Retreat - General Info, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- VEA, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- VEA, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- VEA, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- VEA File, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- VEA Amendment, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- VEA AMMD, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- VEA-Final Claim Worksheets, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- VEA Memos, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- VEA 71-72, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Monthly Expenditure Reports, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Lease File, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- House Memos, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- House Calendar, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Pierre Douyon, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- NDEA-VA 70-027-004, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Redesign Part II -Ted Turone-, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- VEA Grant 72-73 Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Planning Grant Close-Out, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Project Planning Grant, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- 72-'73 VEA Grant and Final Invoice, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- New York- Inservice, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Exp Labs Final Invoice, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Growth Group Close out, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Tech. Asst Conf, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Growth Group, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Experimental Workshops, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Expenditure Farms, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Exp Labs Close Out, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Payables, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Renovations, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Fire Repairs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Rental Agreement, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Book-based income, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Humanistic Education, Center for, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- NDEA Proposal, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Jesuit Retreat House Blueprint, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Proposed work to be done at Center of Humanistic Education, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Contractual Agreement, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Grants, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Affective Concerns In Education, 1971 September (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Contracts and Grant Proposals, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Misc. Articles, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Misc. Articles, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Application of T.S. Concepts to Effective Planning and Management Etc, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Experimental Workshop Series, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Education for Life-Style Change, 1973 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Categories of Decision Making, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Articles by Staff, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Inservice Report, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- How To Increase Motivation Through Climate and Structure, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Game Rules, 1971; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Frequency Chart, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Force Field Analysis, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- A Workshop for Fit. "An Introduction to Humanistic Education", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Policy Group Memos, 1970; 1971; 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Planning for Living, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Problem Solving, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Participation in Decision Making, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Occasional Papers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Proposals, 1970-1972; Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Recapitulations Workshops, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- VEA Proposals, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- VEA Proposals, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- VEA Proposals, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- VEA Bronx Community College Workshop [1 of 2], 1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- VEA Bronx Community College Workshop [2 of 2], 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- VEA Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Work Relationships, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Values Workshop, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Technology of OD, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Schenectady Community College, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- System Entry, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Tompkins Cortland Community College, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Redesign Workshop, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Left-Handed Teaching, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Annual Report, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Renewing Educational System, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Educational Opportunity Forum, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Contract # 0010, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Contract # 0012, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Contract # 0013, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Contract # 0014, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Contract # 0015, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Contract # 0016, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Contract # 0017, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Contract # 0018, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Contract # 0020, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Contract # 0022, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Contract # 0023, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Contract # 0025, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Contract # 0026, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Contract # 0030, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Contract # 0042, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Contract # 0043, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Contract # 0001, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Contract # 0002, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Contract # 0003, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Contract # 0004, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Contract # 0005, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Contract # 0006, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Contract # 0007, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Contract # 0008, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Contract # 0009, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Criterion Conference, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Contract # 0080, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Contract # 0074, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Contract # 0070, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Contract # 0055, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- NYSPGA Organization Development Workshop Contact and Outline, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Contract # 0063, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Proposed Contracts, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Grant 007, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Contractual Agreements, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Material on the Workshop on Growth-Oriented Groups, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- PTE- An Occasional Paper #1,2,3, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- "Humanistic Education" from Education Technology, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- The Center for Humanistic Education, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 43)
- "Is There a Western Philosophical Model for Black Experience", 1973 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- The Origami Game Leaders Manual, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Student Achievement Strategy Guides, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- "Improving Group Decision Making", Undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Intervening in Education Processes Project Completion [1 of 2], 1973 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Intervening in Education Processes Project Completion [2 of 2], 1973 (Box 4, Folder 49)
- "Intervening in Educational Processes" Project Completion Report, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 50)
- "Intervening in Educational Processes" Project Completion Report Partial, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Workshop Report- Work Relationship and How to Change Them, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Preliminary Education Report on the 1972-1973 Inservice Program for Elementary and Secondary School Counselors (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Towards the Development of a Core Humanistic Education Curriculum Prospectus, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Aiding Productive Lay-Professional Interaction, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Aiding Productive Lay-Professional Interaction Appendices 1-3, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Aiding Productive Lay-Professional Interaction Appendices 4-7, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Aiding Productive Lay-Professional Interactions Supplemental Material, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- The Journal of Applied Behavioral Science Vol.8 No.5, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Intervening in Educational Process Report and Supplements [1 of 2], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Intervening in Educational Process Report and Supplements [2 of 2], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Changing A Community College Presentation [1 of 2], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Changing A Community College Presentation [2 of 2], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Redefining 'Blackness' and 'Whiteness' Workshop, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- "The Experience of Living" Workshop, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- "A Project in Humanistic Education for Occupational Education Development in the Two-Year Colleges of New York State, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Project Evaluation Report, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Program Synopsis, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- " Recapitulations" Proposal, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Erling, Norm, Rich Workpapers and Info, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Blank Forms and Contracts, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Budget Request Forms, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Current Budget, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Budget & Account Memos, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Associate's Agreement, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Financial Statements, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Personnel Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Proj. Pioneer, Undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Career/Open Education Development Program, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Deficit Report, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Deficit Correspondence and Workpapers, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Final Report & Notes, Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
- 72 & Prior Budgets (Historical), 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Financial and Budget Correspondence, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Outside Group Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Internal Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- "Making Sense" 14mm Film, Undated (Box 6, Item 1)
- "Build Yourself A City" 14mm Film, Undated (Box 6, Item 2)
- "What's New At School" Open Educational Development Program (BOCES, Bethlehem, CHE-SUNYA) 14mm Film, Undated (Box 6, Item 3)